Register of the Constantine L. Zakhartchenko papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Constantine L. Zakhartchenko Papers
1915-1989
77087
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 20 microfilm reels (3.4 linear feet)
These papers contain the personal documents and correspondence of Constantine L'vovich Zakhartchenko, a Russian émigré and aeronautical engineer. In the course of his engineering career, Zakhartchenko was involved with the design and development of numerous aircraft, aircraft components, and missiles, including the jet engine afterburner, the McDonnell ZHJD-1 twin-engine helicopter, and ZAUM-N-Z cruise missile.
Zakhartchenko, Constantine L.
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives and the Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
A portion of the collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Originals
In part, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Biography
Constantine L’vovich Zakhartchenko was born in Lublin, Russia, on January 17, 1900. A graduate of the Imperial Naval Academy, he served as a midshipman, second mate, and second officer from 1916 to 1920. Immigrating to the United States, Zakhartchenko enrolled at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, from which he graduated in 1923 and embarked on an engineering career. Zakhartchenko began work as an assistant chief engineer at the Shiuchow Aircraft Works in Kwangtung, China, from 1934 to 1943 and later worked for the McDonnel Aircraft Corporation and the United States Naval Ordnance Experimental Unit at the Potomac River Naval Command.
He helped design and develop numerous aircraft, aircraft components, and missiles, including the jet engine afterburner, the McDonnell ZHJD-1 twin engine helicopter, and ZAUM-N-Z cruise missile. In 1956, he received the U. S. Navy Distinguished Civilian Service Award
Constantine L. Zakhartchenko died in 1987 in Washington, D.C.
Chronology
1900 January 17 Born, Lublin, Russia
1916-1920 Imperial Naval Academy, Russia Active duty as midshipman, second mate, second officer
1923 Graduated, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA
1934-1943 Assistant chief engineer, Shiuchow Aircraft Works, Kwantung, China
1943-1948 Chief engineer, Helicopter & Propulsion research division, McDonnell Aircraft Corp.
1950-1956 Director of Engineering, Product engineering department, United States Naval Ordnance Experimental Unit, Potomac River Naval Command
1956 Received U.S. Navy distinguished civilian service award
1987 Died, Washington, D.C., U.S.A.
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers contain the personal documents and correspondence of Constantine L'vovich Zakhartchenko, a Russian émigré and aeronautical engineer. In the course of his engineering career, Zakhartchenko was involved with the design and development of numerous aircraft, aircraft components, and missiles, including the jet engine afterburner, the McDonnell ZHJD-1 twin engine helicopter, and ZAUM-N-Z cruise missile.
The Subject File includes materials on the professional interests of Zakhartchenko, as well as his activity as an Imperial Naval Academy alumnus. Major themes include aeronautical engineering, politics and issues relating to space and arms race, Soviet politics, and history.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Speeches and writings, Writings by others, Subject file, Photographs, and Printed matter
Related Material
Nikolai N. Aleksandrov Papers, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
Constantine L. Zakhartchenko papers, 1920-1976, Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace
Constantine L. Zakhartchenko papers, 1945-1980, University of Wyoming
Aeronautics. Military--China.; Aerospace engineering--United States--20th century.; American society for Russian naval history.; Association of former Russian naval officers in America.; Photographs.; Russia--History.; Russian emigres--United States.; Soviet science and technology.; Soviet Union--Aeronautical engineering.; Soviet Union--Armed Forces.; Space race--Soviet Union--History.
- General Documents, 1915-1989 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, writings, certificates, airplane designs, blueprints, technical and financial reports, telegrams, contracts, printed matter, and photographs, relating to engineering and military aspects of Chinese aviation, aeronautical engineering in the United States, and Russian émigré affairs. Original Materials acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
- Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
  Scope and Contents
  Original copies of documents are housed at Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary. Microfilm use copies avilable at Hoover Archives.
  Downloadable PDF file of the Microfilm Reel Content Guide
  - Biographical file, 1920-1987, undated
    Affidavit, applications, biographical sketches, calling cards, certificates, estate documents, funeral dispositions, licenses, membership cards, Morskoe uchilishche documents, identification documents, travel documents, and vaccination records. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
    - Affidavit, 1982 (Folder 1: 1)
    - Applications, employment and related, 1920-1969, undated (Folder 1: 2)
      Includes related correspondence and notes
    - Biographical sketches and related data, 1924-1978, undated (Folder 1: 3)
      Includes clipping
    - Calling cards (Folder 1: 4)
    - Certificates, licenses, 1920-1982, undated (Folder 1: 5)
    - Estate description, undated (Folder 1: 6)
    - Family file, 1946-1958, undated (Folder 1: 7)
      Zakharchenko, Mary. Clipping, notes, photocopy of baptismal certificate
    - Funeral arrangement dispositions, 1979-1983 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Membership cards, 1958-1987, undated (Folder 1: 9)
    - Morskoe uchilishche documents, undated photocopies of originals, 1920 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Identification documents, 1920-1929, undated (Folder 1: 11)
    - Travel documents, 1940-1943, undated (Folder 1: 12)
    - Vaccination records, 1939-1942 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1989 and undated.
    Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
    - General
      - Condolences, 1951-1985 (Folder 1: 14)
      - Morskoe uchilishche alumni
        - 1947-1969, undated (Folder 1: 15)
        - 1970-1985 (Folder 1: 16)
    - Unidentified, 1923-1985, undated (Folder 1: 17)
    - Adams, Eleanor, 1984 (Folder 1: 18)
    - Aksakov, Sergei, 1973-1985, undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Aleksander, Eveline and Petr, undated (Folder 2: 2)
      Includes clippings and two short stories
    - Aleksandrov, Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1962-1985, undated (Folder 2: 3)
    - Alekseev, Viktoriia, undated (Folder 2: 4)
    - Althausen, Theodore L., 1974-1986, undated (Folder 2: 5)
      Includes family photographs, typescript of short story
    - Ambler, Ernest, 1984 (Folder 2: 6)
    - American Astronautical Association, 1958-1980 (Folder 2: 7)
    - American Ordnance Association, 1957 (Folder 2: 8)
    - American Society for Russian Naval History, 1958-1972 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Ansah, Samuel, 1979 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Astin, Allen V. and Margaret, 1953 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Aviation Week & Space Technology, 1977 (Folder 2: 12)
    - Beauchamp, Gerry, Captain, 1935-1978, undated (Folder 2: 13)
      Includes correspondence relating to the Shiuchow Aircraft Works in China, and typescript as well as printed copy of memoirs relating to aircraft development in China
    - Belavenets, Ivan, 1953-1961, undated (Folder 2: 14)
      Includes five prints
    - Bert, Gordon N. le, 1972-1980, undated (Folder 2: 15)
      Includes copies of articles and drafts of memoirs relating to James McDonnell
    - Bevier, Louis, 1944 (Folder 2: 16)
    - Borodin, B., 1976 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Brookes, Evelyn, 1931 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Butakov, V., 1970-1981, undated (Folder 3: 2)
    - Bryant, John H., 1963, 1980 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Chaiko, Marguerite and Walter, 1964-1985 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Chan, Wing Kon, 1967-1984 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Charles, Robert Horne, 1948 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Chekhov Publishing House, 1951-1956 (Folder 3: 7)
    - Chien, C. T., 1950-1977 (Folder 3: 8)
      Includes Chien's autobiography in Chinese, and three prints
    - Chinese Air Force, 1945-1960 (Folder 3: 9)
      Includes two prints, and clippings
    - Christian Anti-Communism Crusade, 1972 (Folder 3: 10)
    - Chulanovskii, Ivan, 1965-1977 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Cooperative Forum, 1957-1973 (Folder 3: 12)
    - Cowling, James G., 1964-1982, undated (Folder 3: 13)
    - Cox, Gertrude, undated (Folder 3: 14)
    - Crumb, Carl, 1970 (Folder 3: 15)
    - Danilov, N., 1968-1975 (Folder 3: 16)
    - Day, C. H., 1948-1967 (Folder 3: 17)
    - District of Columbia Society of Professional Engineers, Inc., 1955-1975 (Folder 3: 18)
    - Diehl, Walter S., 1970 (Folder 3: 19)
    - Doberly Dobroliubov, V. J., 1951 (Folder 3: 20)
    - Doblhoff, F. L. von, 1958 (Folder 3: 21)
    - Dolgikh, Aleksandr, 1970-1981 (Folder 3: 22)
    - Dooley, L. R., 1948 (Folder 3: 23)
    - Drage, Charles, 1954-1970, undated (Folder 3: 24)
      Includes clippings
    - Durant, Frederick C., 1958 (Folder 3: 25)
    - Edwards, Martin L, 1954 (Folder 3: 26)
    - Elfenbein, J. A., 1964 (Folder 3: 27)
    - Endersby, Victor A., 1970-1979 (Folder 3: 28)
    - Erdman, Frank H., 1958 (Folder 3: 29)
    - Fedorov, Konstantin
      - 1960-1969 (Folder 3: 30)
      - 1970-1974 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Folkert, Vsevolod, 1982, undated (Folder 4: 2)
    - Furnas, C. C., 1948-1973 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Gail, Albert, 1948 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Garin, Aleksei Nikolaevich, 1959-1984, undated (Folder 4: 5)
    - Gavrishev, Boris Ivanovich, 1955-1961 (Folder 4: 6)
    - General Motors Engineering Staff, 1971-1973 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Gering, Aleksei A., 1971 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Glad, Andy, 1967-1976, undated (Folder 4: 9)
    - Gladkevich, Nikolai, undated (Folder 4: 10)
    - Goodman, John, 1982-1983, undated (Folder 4: 11)
    - Gordev, G. V., 1975-1983 (Folder 4: 12)
    - Greene, William L., 1944 (Folder 4: 13)
    - Hadary, Caroline H., 1980 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Hiller Helicopters, 1951 (Folder 4: 15)
    - Holloway, Joe T., undated (Folder 4: 16)
    - Hooper, Edwin B., 1960-1981 (Folder 4: 17)
    - Hoover Institution of War, Revolution and Peace, 1975-1984 (Folder 4: 18)
    - Hopper (?), Wale C., undated (Folder 4: 19)
    - Hyatt, Abraham, 1960, undated (Folder 4: 20)
    - Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences, 1948-1975, undated (Folder 4: 21)
    - Islamov, Il'ia, 1972 (Folder 4: 22)
    - Iunakov, Mikhail A., 1981 (Folder 4: 23)
    - Iur'eva Cowling, Militsa, undated
      General note
      See Correspondence/Yurieva, Militsa
    - Ivanovskii, Arsenii, 1961, undated (Folder 4: 24)
    - Kaiser, Kim, 1959 (Folder 4: 25)
    - Kaloucek, Walter, undated (Folder 4: 26)
    - Kazanskii, Lev and Vladimir, 1975, undated (Folder 4: 27)
    - Khotuntsov, Sergei Ivanovich, 1977 (Folder 4: 28)
    - Kibort, Leonid, 1945-1982, undated (Folder 4: 29)
    - Kingham, Elizabeth Winks, 1961, undated (Folder 4: 30)
    - Koltypin, Petr N., 1980 (Folder 4: 31)
    - Korcyn-Zukowski, Borys, 1976-1985 (Folder 4: 32)
      Includes newspaper clippings
    - Korvin-Krukovskii, B. V., 1968-1980 (Folder 4: 33)
    - Korvin-Krukovskii, Evgeniia A., 1960-1979 (Folder 4: 34)
    - Kostenko, Vladimir, 1965 (Folder 4: 35)
    - Krone, Norris, undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Kulish, Sergei Vasil'evich, 1923 (Folder 5: 2)
    - Kumasheva, Elizaveta, 1975-1976, undated (Folder 5: 3)
    - Lamm, R. A., 1953-1984 (Folder 5: 4)
    - LePage, Wynn Laurence, 1958 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Lesley and Roberts Tailors, 1953-1967 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Lester, E. M., 1958 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Lewis, Will A., 1960 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Lipow, Eugene G., Dr., undated (Folder 5: 9)
    - Louie, Harry, 1966-1985 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Lym, Sarah, 1966 (Folder 5: 11)
    - Lynn Chu, General, 1943, undated (Folder 5: 12)
    - Mack Motor Truck Company, 1956 (Folder 5: 13)
    - Mclaurin Fund, 1980-1985 (Folder 5: 14)
    - Madden, James J., 1981, undated (Folder 5: 15)
    - Magerovskii, Lev Florianovich, 1972 (Folder 5: 16)
    - Maidanovich, N. L., 1978-1981 (Folder 5: 17)
    - Malley, P. Garnet, 1977-1984 (Folder 5: 18)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1971-1985, undated (Folder 5: 19)
    - McDaniel, Randall, 1983 (Folder 5: 20)
    - Medvedev, Nikolai Ivanovich, 1958-1964 (Folder 5: 21)
    - Meyer, Vera F., 1980 (Folder 5: 22)
    - Midwest Research Institute, 1953 (Folder 5: 23)
    - Miller, Rene H., 1944-1985 (Folder 5: 24)
    - National Maritime Musuem, 1960 (Folder 5: 25)
    - National Broadcasting Company, 1983 (Folder 5: 26)
    - Nedler, S., 1976, undated (Folder 5: 27)
    - New York Times, 1972 (Folder 5: 28)
    - Nielsen, A. F., 1964-1985 (Folder 5: 29)
    - Oberg, James E., 1956-1981 (Folder 5: 30)
    - Ohio State University, 1956-1959 (Folder 5: 31)
    - Oliveri, Harriet, 1979 (Folder 5: 32)
    - Patterson, A. L., 1948-1985 (Folder 5: 33)
    - Patterson, W. C., 1954 (Folder 5: 34)
    - Pearce, Susan, 1982-1983 (Folder 5: 35)
    - Prokhorov, Viktor, 1959-1984 (Folder 5: 36)
    - Quaritch, Bernard, 1953 (Folder 5: 37)
    - Rao, Dhanvanda M., 1981 (Folder 5: 38)
    - Richardson, Bellows, Henry & Company, Inc., 1956-1957 (Folder 5: 39)
    - Reaction Motors, Inc., 1946-1947 (Folder 5: 40)
    - Reynardson, Birch, undated (Folder 5: 41)
    - Ritchie, D. J., 1959-1978 (Folder 5: 42)
    - Russian Naval Officers Association, 1923-1984, undated (Box-folder 6: 1)
      Includes newspaper clippings, one negative, and two prints
    - Russian Student Fund, 1955-1965 (Folder 6: 2)
    - Salerno, Miriam, 1942-1985, undated (Folder 6: 3)
      Includes clippings, notes and related materials on Malta
    - Scherberg, Max, 1950 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Schroeder, Henry, 1955 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Schwarz, Dr., 1984 (Folder 6: 6)
    - Scott, Alan, 1959 (Folder 6: 7)
    - Scripps-Howard Newspaper Alliance, 1956 (Folder 6: 8)
    - Security Storage Company, 1986 (Folder 6: 9)
    - Senkevich, A., 1958 (Folder 6: 10)
    - Shakhovskaia, Kseniia, undated (Folder 6: 11)
    - Sharpe, Mitchell R., 1972-1974 (Folder 6: 12)
      Includes two negatives, and eight prints
    - Sheldon, D., undated (Folder 6: 13)
    - Shemanskii, Iurii A., 1974-1982 (Folder 6: 14)
      Includes nine prints
    - Sheng, James, 1953-1984, undated (Folder 6: 15)
    - Sheremet'ev, Sergei, undated (Folder 6: 16)
    - Shimanovskii, Iurii Olegovich, 1983-1985 (Folder 6: 17)
    - Simons, Richard W., 1962-1966 (Folder 6: 18)
    - Siu, Henry M., 1964 (Folder 6: 19)
    - Slattery, Frank P., 1946 (Folder 6: 20)
    - Smith, Stanley G., 1956 (Folder 6: 21)
    - Sokolovskii, Sergei, 1970 (Folder 6: 22)
    - Solonevich, Boris, 1963-1981 (Folder 6: 23)
      Includes six prints
    - St. Joseph's Nursing Home, 1981 (Folder 6: 24)
    - St. Nicholas Cathedral, Washington, D.C., 1961-1981 (Folder 6: 25)
    - St. Thomas Apostolic Church, 1983-1984 (Folder 6: 26)
    - Starkovskii, Nikolai, 1961-1971 (Folder 6: 27)
    - Staub, Nancy L., 1980-1984, undated (Folder 6: 28)
      See also Photographs/Staub, Nancy
    - Stepanov, Alla and Vladimir, 1975 (Folder 6: 29)
    - Sterhardt, Mrs., 1974 (Folder 6: 30)
    - Stogov, P. E., 1969 (Folder 6: 31)
    - Sukhanov, Ivan Mikhailovich, undated (Folder 6: 32)
    - Sukhanova-Watson, Mariia, 1974 (Folder 6: 33)
    - Sutherland, J. F., 1979-1980 (Folder 6: 34)
    - Swift, Margaret, 1982-1984 (Folder 6: 35)
    - Tarbox, Elmer L., 1956-1961 (Folder 6: 36)
    - Thayes, John B., 1943 (Folder 6: 37)
    - Tolley, Kemp, 1963 (Folder 6: 38)
    - Tolstaia, E., 1957-1962 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Tower, Jeremiah, 1970-1985 (Folder 7: 2)
      See also Subject file/Tower, Jeremiah
      Includes two prints.
    - Tower, W. S., Jr., undated (Folder 7: 3)
    - Turkerman, Lucien P., 1970 (Folder 7: 4)
    - United States Naval Academy, 1962-1963, 1975 (Folder 7: 5)
    - United States Naval Institute, 1953, 1973, undated (Folder 7: 6)
    - University of Wyoming, Transportation History Foundation, 1970-1981 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Vesper, Gerald W., 1974 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Vesselago, George M., 1958 (Folder 7: 9)
    - Viazemskaia, Ol'ga Dmitrievna, 1961-1964 (Folder 7: 10)
    - Visochin, Vladimir V., 1961-1977 (Folder 7: 11)
    - Vladimir (Sukhobok), Abbott, 1980 (Folder 7: 12)
    - Vuckovic, Jovica, 1977 (Folder 7: 13)
    - Wadkovsky, Basil, 1928 (Folder 7: 14)
    - Ward, Roger, 1946-1969 (Folder 7: 15)
    - Washington Star, 1977-1980 (Folder 7: 16)
    - Weiss, Harry, 1958 (Folder 7: 17)
    - Werlich, Robert, 1966-1969 (Folder 7: 18)
    - Whitcomb, K. H., 1923 (Folder 7: 19)
    - White House, 1958-1977 (Folder 7: 20)
    - Winder Aircraft Corporation, 1954 (Folder 7: 21)
    - Winter, John, 1956-1975 (Folder 7: 22)
    - Withington, Frederic S., 1961-1982, undated (Folder 7: 23)
    - Woodward, Harper, 1958-1979 (Folder 7: 24)
    - Yuen, Frank Der, 1953-1985 (Folder 7: 25)
    - Yurieva, Militsa, 1929-1974, undated (Folder 7: 26)
    - Zagurskii, Nikolai, 1948-1964 (Folder 7: 27)
    - Zaionchkovskii, Aleksei Ivanovich, 1955-1976 (Folder 7: 28)
    - Zakhartchenko, Mary, 1944-1946 (Folder 7: 29)
    - Zakhartchenko, Nina L'vovna, 1962-1989, undated (Folder 7: 30)
      Includes seven prints
    - Zelenoy, Militsa, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - Zimmermann, P. G., 1956-1962 (Folder 8: 2)
    - Zorov, Vladimir M., 1965, undated (Folder 8: 3)
  - Speeches and writings, 1947-1967, undated
    Articles, clippings, notes, report, speech, arranged chronologically by title
    - Notes, 1968, undated (Folder 8: 4)
    - Untitled speech on the development of helicopters, 1947 (Folder 8: 5)
      Typescript
    - "Singapurskaia ekspeditsiia na shesterke v aprele 1920 g.,", undated (Folder 8: 6)
      Clipping
    - "Stars or obscurity,", 1952 (Folder 8: 7)
    - "Helicopter Rotor Construction,", 1954 (Folder 8: 8)
    - "Comment and recommendations based on unclassified USSR literature relevant to guided missiles art,", 1957 (Folder 8: 9)
    - "Basic objectives of the Soviet space program,", 1959 (Folder 8: 10)
    - "Trends in Soviet space activities," The Bendix corporation research laboratories division, Report No. 1881, 1961 (Folder 8: 11)
      Printed copy, includes related materials and newspaper clippings
    - "USSR strategic nuclear armament,", 1967 (Folder 8: 12)
  - Writings by others, 1933-1985 and undated.
    Arranged alphabetically by author
    - Chaiko, Michael V., "Vagabonds by choice. Last midshipmen of the imperial Russian navy,", 1958 (Folder 8: 13-14)
      Typescript, includes related correspondence and corrections entered in 1985
    - Feodoroff, Constantin
      - "As I remember it,", 1972 (Folder 8: 15)
        Typescript, includes related correspondence
      - "Block ships,", 1972 (Folder 8: 16)
      - "Blow, wind, blow,", undated (Folder 8: 17)
        Typescript, pp. 1-180
      - "Blow, wind, blow,", undated (Box-folder 9: 1)
        Typescript, pp. 181-346
      - "Notes on labor question in U.S.S.R.,", 1963 (Folder 9: 2)
        Typescript, includes related correspondence and clipping
      - "The nations enslaved by communism,", 1964 (Folder 9: 3)
    - Garin, Aleksei N., "Stikhotvoreniia, 1915-1928,", 1974 (Folder 9: 4)
      Typescript, includes related correspondence and notes
    - Garina, Ekaterina, "Stikhotvoreniia, 1923-193...,", undated (Folder 9: 5)
    - Gusev-Orenburgskii, Sergei Ivanovich, "Striela; razskaz,", 1933 (Folder 9: 6)
      Printed copy, signed by author. Includes related correspondence
    - Shemanskii, Iurii, "Crossing the equator in a ship's boat,", 1981 (Folder 9: 7)
      Printed copy, includes three prints
    - Stepanov, Iu., "Pod poliarnoi zviezdoi,", 1930-1940 (Folder 9: 8)
      Photocopy of manuscript
  - Subject file, 1924-1985 and undated.
    Applications, articles, blueprints, brochures, bulletins, catalog, certificates, clippings, contracts, correspondence, drafts, government documents, invoices, lectures, lists, maps, memos, minutes, notes, patents, printed matter, prints, receipts, report, arranged alphabetically by subject
    - Aeronautics. Military--China, undated (Folder 9: 9)
    - Aerospace engineering--United States--20th century, 1924-1980, undated (Folder 9: 10-15)
      Includes blueprints, clippings, contracts, correspondence, drafts, government documents, notes, patents, prints
    - Aerospace engineering--United States--20th century, 1924-1980, undated (Box-folder 10: 1-12)
    - American Society for Russian Naval History, 1958-1965, undated
      See also Subject file/Association of Russian Imperial Naval Officers in America, Inc.
      Includes materials related to N. N. Aleksandrov, Dean of Holy Trinity Seminary.
      - General, 1959-1965, undated (Folder 10: 13)
      - Certificate of incorporation, 1958-1965 (Folder 10: 14)
        Includes application for absolute charter, related correspondence, minutes and other materials
      - Correspondence, 1958-1965, undated (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Anti-communist movements, 1979-1985, undated (Folder 11: 2)
      Brochures, clippings
    - Association of Russian Imperial Naval Officers in America, Inc., 1953-1982, undated
      See also Subject file/American Society for Russian Naval History
      - General, 1951-1974, undated (Folder 11: 3)
      - Bulletin
        - 1953-1957 (Folder 11: 4)
        - 1958-1963 (Folder 11: 5)
        - 1964-1966 (Folder 11: 6)
        - 1967-1969 (Folder 11: 7)
        - 1970-1972 (Folder 11: 8)
        - 1973-1976 (Box-folder 12: 1)
        - 1977-1982 (Folder 12: 2)
      - Morskogo uchilishcha vypusk 1920 goda
        - 30 liet spustia, 1950 (Folder 12: 3)
          Printed copy, numbered 2
        - 30 liet spustia. Dopolnenie No. 1, 1951 (Folder 12: 4)
        - 30 liet spustia. Dopolnenie No. 2, 1952 (Folder 12: 5)
        - 30 liet spustia. Dopolnenie No. 3, 1953 (Folder 12: 6)
        - 30 liet spustia. Dopolnenie No. 4, 1954 (Folder 12: 7)
        - 37 liet spustia, 1957 (Folder 12: 8)
        - 38 liet spustia, 1958 (Box-folder 13: 1)
        - 40 liet spustia, 1960 (Folder 13: 2)
        - 46 liet spustia, 1966 (Folder 13: 3)
          Printed copy
      - Correspondence, 1954-1964, undated (Folder 13: 4)
        Letters addressed to Nikolai N. Aleksandrov
      - Lists, undated (Folder 13: 5)